JONATHAN COTHRAN

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

| Baltimore, MD 21211 • (301) 641-4648 • jonathan@coth.dev • https://info.coth.dev |
|--|
| Professional Summary |
| Dynamic technology professional specializing in API development and web services. Over three years' experience delivering performant data architectures for high visibility features. Training in cloud computing, service-oriented architecture, and data analytics. Agile adaptor of latest development libraries and cloud-based solutions. |
| Professional History |
| Software Developer, 01/2022 to the present National Center for Biotechnology Information Guidehouse Digital - Bethesda, MD |
| Design and build a data-integrated web page serving current knowledge in biomedical data |
| Serve specialized data integration cycles to reliably serve expansive SARS-COV-2 informatics in real-time |
| Maintain Extract Transform Load (ETL) systems serving globally scoped research needs |
| Provide programming client interfaces for data driven bio-sciences |
| Software Developer, 02/2020 to 01/2022 OpenPath Products - Annapolis, MD |
| Expanded mobile application by developing high-performance Java-based Natural Language Processing (NLP) service |
| Successfully scaled to one million weekly NLP users to guide and inform finance and investment decisions |
| Innovated NLP capabilities through customized data-science web services |
| Integrated unique Python and Linux expertise to solve cross-disciplinary team challenges |
| Design to delivery on critical path projects |
| Implemented automated testing solutions to ensure bug-free production deployments |
| Research Specialist, 04/2017 to 08/2018 University of Illinois at Chicago - Chicago, IL |
| Established computational research methods for physiology lab group |
| Provided in-house ImageJ extensions to obtain pivotal microscopy analyses |
| Facilitated high-impact publications by formalizing experimental protocol |
| Research and Development Scientist, 05/2016 to 12/2016 Thermo Fisher Scientific - Frederick, MD |
| Developed major line of products for global vaccine research needs |
| Core Skills and Competencies |
| Python Golang React Java CLI Application Development Mongo NoSQL Git Repository Management SQL + |
| Relational Databases IaaS + PaaS Provisioning Linux Bash Shell AWS + GCP Cloud Protocol Buffer |
| Specification HTTP/2 – gRPC Services Agile Methodologies Analytical Problem Solving Multidisciplinary |
| Collaboration Strategic Requirement Planning |
| Education and Training |

Bachelor of Science: Biological Sciences, 2015 **University of Maryland, College Park** - College Park, MD